Alyea mss., 1926-1973 LMC 2585
Lilly Library
Alyea mss.
1926-1973
Lilly Library
Alyea, Dorothy C. (Dorothy Collins), 1898-1974
LMC 2585
3 Boxes 3 standard
The Alyea mss., 1926-1973, consists of the writings of poet Dorothy Collins Alyea, 1898-1974.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 2007, 2008
Biographical Note
Dorothy Collins Alyea, born in 1898, lived in Montclair, New Jersey. Throughout her career, she worked with the Monclair Women's Club, the League of Women Voters, and the Planned Parenthood Association. She married her husband, Ethan Alyea, in 1924.
Dorothy was a fellow of the MacDowell Colony in Peterborough, New Hampshire, in 1947. She won the first prize at the Rochester Poetry Festival in 1967, and she won the membership contest of the Poetry Society of America in 1973.
Alyea's poems appeared in a wide variety of newspapers and magazines, including The Chicago Tribune Magazine, Christian Century, Forum, Ohio University Review, Oregonian Verse, Poetry, The Rochester Democrat, and Chronicle, and The Saturday Review of Literature. She also published two books of poetry: All My Argument in 1935 and Beach Fire in 1951. Alyea died in New York in July 1974.
Scope and Contents
Present in the collection are autograph drafts of poems; typed and carbon copy drafts as well as final versions; handwritten drafts on notepads; and various clippings of published poems. Also included are a travel diary, short stories, some scrapbook materials, a published copy of the 1926 Forum, and a DVD of a 2007 reading of Alyea's poetry and short stories.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically. Box 1, containing drafts of Alyea's poetry, is in original order.
American poetry--20th century.; Short stories, American; Essays.; Alyea, Dorothy C. (Dorothy Collins), 1898-1974
- Writings
  - Poetry
    - Poetry Drafts (18 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
    - Poems: 1935-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poems: 1951-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Iridescent Afternoon and Other Poems, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Silver Thaw (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbook (Printed Poems), 1935-09-09-1952-03-30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Printed Forum July 1926, 1926-07 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Short Stories
    - A Telephone Rang (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Agreeable Giant, The (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Angel Bell and the Tramp Professor (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Button-Button (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cherry Hill (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Creative Imagination (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Helen Gage (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Henry and his Girl (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The House Party Murder (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Mr. Moses' Garden (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Senhor Seraphim (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Shadows (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Yosemite National Park (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Published Stories (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Essays
    - The Irish Dramatists (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Untitled Essays (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Audio Visual Materials
  - Digital Poems and Short Stories, 2007-12-13 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Personal Papers
  - Travel Diary (Box 2, Folder 7)